Before we take any action, we need to talk about universal precautions.
These are the steps you take to keep yourself safe while you are helping someone else.
The most important rule in first aid is to protect yourself first.
You should always assume that all blood and bodily fluids, like saliva or vomit, are infectious,
so you must handle them with extreme care.
Using personal protective equipment, or PPE, is ideal.
If PPE isn't available in an emergency, you'll need to use your best judgment to provide
care as safely as you can.
We highly recommend wearing non-latex gloves whenever you are providing any kind of aid
to an injured person.
If you are worried about splashes of blood or vomit, use eye protection and a mask to
keep you safe.
Once you are finished, make sure to dispose of all your used PPE properly so no one else
comes into contact with it.
If you do happen to get exposed to someone else's blood or body fluids, don't panic.
Your first step is to immediately wash the area with soap and water.
If you suspect there was any cross-contamination or a significant exposure, be sure to report
the incident to your healthcare provider right away.